Mark W. Batten Papers
Mark W. Batten Papers
1951-1966
Batten, Mark Wilfred.
0.5 linear ft.
British sculptor and author, president of Royal Society of British Sculptors, 1956-1961. Collection contains manuscript and published articles, notes, books and clippings.
148835
Biographical History
Mark Wilfred Batten (1905-1993) was a British sculptor known for his skill in direct carving. One of his most famous works is The Diogenist, in Hopton-wood stone (Derbyshire marble).
Born in England on 21 Jul 1905, Batten studied at various British art schools. Although he began to experiment with sculpture on his own in 1927, learning stone carving in the granite mason's yards in Cornwall, he exhibited only drawings and paintings until he was in his thirties. In 1936 he began exhibiting his sculpture, including a show at the Royal Academy in 1939. During World War II he served in the Life Guards but quickly returned to his art, exhibiting widely and receiving many commissions for sculpture for public buildings. Batten was President of the Royal Society of British Sculptors (1956-1961) and wrote several books and numerous articles on sculpture.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mark W. Batten Papers contains correspondence, manuscripts and published material.
Correspondence consists of a single outgoing letter by Batten.
Manuscripts contains articles, portions of a book, captions, notes, a speech, several unidentified manuscripts and related materials.
Published material includes articles by and about Batten, copies of his books, and newspapers clippings by and about Batten and his work.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically by type and within that by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Batten, Mark Wilfred.; Royal Society of British Sculptors.; Art, Modern -- 20th century.; Sculpture -- Technique.; Sculpture -- 20th century.; Sculpture, Modern -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- Great Britain.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mark W. Batten, 1965.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing, undated (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles
    - "The artist is still tied to a craft", circa 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - "The case for direct carving", 1958 (Box 1)
    - "The cult of experimentation for its own sake" (Box 1)
    - "Fashion in art" (Box 1)
    - "International Congress of the Arts (Dubrovnik)", 1957 (Box 1)
    - "Originality can be something other than stunts with technique" (Box 1)
    - "Sculpture as a contemporary outlook", circa 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - "Sculpture", article in Modham's Companion Encyclopedia (Box 1)
    - "What sculpture is" (Box 1)
  - Articles and notes
    - "A rational basis for my aesthetic opinions" (Box 1)
  - Books
    - Chapter I, "Considering Sculpture in General and Stone Sculpture in Particular," from Direct Carving in Stone (Box 1)
  - Book reviews
    - In the Studio, Nov 1956 (Box 1)
  - Captions
    - for article, "Authentication and dating of ancient Greeks" (Box 1)
    - for book, Direct Carving in Stone (Box 1)
  - Notes
    - Various (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Untitled, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Unidentified
    - Manuscripts, untitled, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Articles about
    - Various, 1952-1953; 1960,; 1963; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Articles by
    - A better way to approach sculpture, 1951; 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Books
    - Direct Carving in Stone, 1966; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Stone Sculpture, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Stone Sculpture by Direct Carving, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - About, 1951-1952; 1959,; undated (Box 1)
    - By, 1956 (Box 1)